"Collagen Supplements for Arthritis"
Nearly a millennium ago,
a medieval nun suggested eating
gelatin to reduce joint pain.
Unfortunately, when it was put
to the test in a multicenter,
randomized double-blind
placebo-controlled trial,
it didn't work.
A dozen years later, looking
at knee and hip osteoarthritis,
there was still
no overall evidence
for collagen supplements
working better than placebo.
However, the latest compilation
of studies purported to show
a benefit for improving
osteoarthritis symptoms.
In one symptom index, it
appeared to help with stiffness,
but not pain or disability.
But, an overall
improvement in symptoms
and a different index of pain
were statistically significant.
If, however, you exclude
the smallest study,
whose authors were employees
of a collagen company,
all of the results
lost clinical importance,
meaning the overall effects
were unnoticeably small.
In fact, every single one was
funded by collagen companies,
or directly run
by company employees.
Another thing you'll
notice about these data
is that with this one exception,
the smaller the study,
the larger the effect.
This pattern is a common sign
of publication bias,
the tendency to do
a whole bunch of small trials,
but publish only the ones
that work to your advantage
and secretly shelve the rest.
Coupled with all of
the conflicts of interest,
concerns have been raised
that additional small studies
may have been conducted
but conveniently disappeared.
And then, other fishy findings
are that smaller doses
appeared to have larger effects,
as did using it
for a shorter amount of time.
Okay, but the last study
was published in 2016.
What's happened since then?
A comprehensive systematic
review published in 2022
was surprised to note
that the last study done
on collagen supplements
for rheumatoid arthritis
was published
more than a decade ago,
and the last osteoarthritis
study was still that 2016 one.
Why?
Well, one possible reason
is the high incidence of
adverse side effects reported
in those taking
collagen supplements,
or another reason may be
that they simply
don't work very well.
I mean, if collagen company
executives truly believed
they were selling
something that worked,
why don't they do more studies?
If they thought collagen had
a decent chance of working,
they could make out
like bandits.
The fact that they haven't
sponsored such a trial
suggests they're
not so confident
it would actually show benefit.
One study has been published
since 2016, the biggest yet,
with more than 150 people.
Funded by a collagen company,
researchers found
a significant drop in knee pain,
and a significant
improvement in knee function
among those randomized
to collagen supplements.
But they also found a
significant drop in knee pain
and improvement in knee function
in those randomized
to the placebo,
with no real difference
between them.
So, the fact that
effectively a sugar pill
worked as well as
the collagen supplements
suggests that
collagen doesn't work.
But that does raise
another point.
If you look at what
was used for controls
in the collagen studies,
it was basically
just sugar or sawdust.
And the same with the
skin studies I talked about
in the last video.
So, even if collagen was found
to be helpful in some way,
there is no proof
that collagen has any effects,
beyond just being
a source of amino acids
like any other protein.
So, if any purported
collagen effect
is just a matter of increased
amino acid availability,
then why not just, like,
have some extra hummus
or something?